[Music]
Jordan Peterson has become a global
celebrity by weaving together mythology
science philosophy and religion into a
compelling theory of everything one of
the most influential philosophers of the
last decades did something similar Ken
Wilber is the creator of integral theory
another attempt to pull together much of
the world's knowledge and spiritual
traditions into a theory of everything
integral theory gained a big following
in the 90s and 2000's and remains
influential after serious health
problems over the last decade Ken Wilber
is now returning to the conversation
what do these two hugely influential
thinkers have in common where do they
disagree and what can they learn from
each other a lot of times when it comes
to Jordan Peterson it's not that I'll
disagree with much of what he says I
agree with much of what he says it's
some of the things that he leaves out I
find this a little bit interesting
because he is clearly an integral
thinker to get the most out of this film
we'll need to introduce a little
integral terminology at the core of
integral theory is the idea that
cultures and societies go through
specific levels of development in the
same way as individuals do becoming more
sophisticated as they develop or grow up
it's an idea that's common to
developmental theorists including
Peterson's favorite Jean Piaget you move
from one knowledge structure to the next
one which includes the previous one and
is better and it's better because it
covers more territory that's how you
know it's better it does the same thing
the old tool does plus some additional
things so it's a definition of better
integral theory represents this
development as a spiral in this film
will mostly be talking about amber
tribalism ethnocentric authoritarian
which first emerged about 5,000 years
ago
orange modern values the rational self
emerged 300 years ago with the liberal
democracies and the beginning of
universal values Green the values of
relativism multiple perspectives
dialogue and consensus human rights
sometimes called postmodern which
emerged fully in the 1960s if they're
healthfully integrated they support each
other but each of them can believe that
their way of looking at the world is the
only true way and then they are mutually
exclusive for Wilbur the incomprehension
between these worldviews is what's
causing many of the worst excesses of
the culture wars above these levels
Wilbur says is another level called
integral or second-tier from this
perspective it's clear that each of the
previous ways of seeing the world has
value and needs to be integrated this
seems like a really good point to talk
about Jordan Peterson yeah what do you
think his success is due to as we
started to get this both polarization
and and then included regression in many
cases these absolute istic retry belies
points of view where people again if
they were discussing their tribe they
were saying this is what my tribe has in
common with this tribe and this tribe
and this service is this is how my types
different from that tribe you need to
serve some sort of special something or
other and again there very well could be
tribes that deserves special attention
certainly but the point is if you're
just emphasizing that and you're not
emphasizing how that tribe is part of a
unified overall tribal structure then
that is just retry belies a ssin that is
regression and the only ultimate end
point of that really is just warfare and
I'm he's just no way around it and
humanity fought 300 thousand years to
get over that stage so among other
things it could bring in women's rights
and bring in an industry
and bring in the end of the intouchables
and start including every minority you
can think of LGBTQ transgender this was
extraordinary but as I started to fall
apart and get rocking went started to
get left out as green became just
extreme absolute istic and started
devolving into neol ism and narcissism
or even regressed to absolutist
ethnocentric the only people you had
supporting these original liberal values
which are absolutely crucial to any
higher stage the whole point about these
stage is the development is that each
higher stage again transcends but
includes the previous stage and grand
and transcendence include orange
transcended and repressed orange that's
definition of pathology that's when the
real problems with that so if you have
an integral thinker and they're looking
out there to see what is really missing
is that's what that's how and it's real
thinker thinks is wait there's a little
bit of truth in all of this however we
including all of these things and you're
thinking that way and you look out there
and and if you are for example a
professor teaching at the university one
of the things you start to notice is
this extraordinary lack of traditional
liberal values
those aren't protective those you get
some lip service to them but again it's
usually in terms of words like the
quality and as we've seen there's two
different definitions of equality
there's orange their quality receives
freedom and there's green equality which
means equity equal outcome versus equal
opportunity and so some of the right of
course for supporting that and a lot of
the people like Dave Rubin
head had set of challenges I'm no longer
leftist and what became real clear is
that left and liberal were no longer the
same the old original leftists were
liberals but the new leftists were
illiberal x' they're anti liberal and
that's a disaster you can't go forward
with that kind of pathology and so if
you're somebody like Jordan Peterson who
is thinking integrally and you're
looking around and seeing what the hell
is going on and you're starting to
notice this and then the government
comes along and says oh and by the way
I'm going to compel your speech that
would send anybody with integrity and
integral thinking over the wall and so
he was up you know all night he did
those three videos you know forcing
unconscious bias retraining and
political correctness and what he saw
happening with that and and the
nightmare of Bill c16 threw him up on
the net went viral and the main cause of
that in my opinion is that is these
orange liberal values of equal
opportunity that we're getting crushed
between the extreme far left of green
and the strong far right of ethnocentric
amber and these liberal values in
between were just getting left out of
the out of the picture and that was a
disaster and that was the thing that at
least put Jordan Peterson on the map and
he was arguing against Bill c16 because
not only that it put into law a
constructivist view of human identity
that was his complaint it had nothing to
transgender people and the people that
attacked him for being anti transgender
had absolutely nothing
to do with that he's very clear about
that
what it was was putting into actual law
a constructivist view of human nature
which by the way is pure green it's pure
postmodern Green viewpoint and that also
is an attack on free speech in the worst
possible way what I found really
fascinating about Jordan Peterson
watching especially the maps of meaning
series is that he is also attempting a
real integral theory of everything what
what was it and you're this this
reminded me very much of your project
how did how do you feel that his thought
maps onto yours and what are the core
differences there are a couple of
different aspects of integral meta
theory that could come to play in here
and and I want to make it as
non-academic as as as as possible one of
the things that I have a really really
deep appreciation of Jordan Peterson for
is the process that I call showing has
to do with what we call four quadrants
and I can I can make that fairly simple
by saying that the four quadrants for
example will shake down into things like
the good the true and the beautiful and
people are fairly aware of that they're
a very widely known widely accepted sort
of Trinity of different types of
knowledge different types of values
different types of methods that we use
and they each have a certain kind of
truth but those whose differ point about
Jordan Pederson is that he has an
enormous amount of respect for objective
science and he's always
anchoring or at least correlating what
he's saying with some sort of neuro
physiological research or
anthropological research or at big five
factor analysis research or so on but
what he realizes is that there are these
other validity claims that aren't just
objective material exterior truth and
these other things are damned important
as a matter of fact they are important
and one of the disasters of the Western
alignment was that it ended up going
from an understanding where what it was
emphasizing critic Charles Taylor the
most dominant idea in the Western
enlightenment was what the French
philosophers called
the system de la nature the great whole
interlocking system as a whole
John Locke actually called it the great
interlocking order the second most
common idea in the Western enlightenment
according to author Lovejoy where's the
great chain of being and we usually
don't think of that with the rest of the
Enlightenment but the great chain of
being was a viewpoint of reality that as
luxury demonstrates in his book called
the great chain of being is the single
most lively adopted overall philosophy
that that the larger percentage of
sensitive educated men and women have
adopted throughout virtually all of our
civilizations up to and including the
Western enlightenment
so when lesser enlightenment started
doing when when the Keppler was
measuring planetary motion and and
Galilee was measuring earthly motion and
Newton was measuring gravitation and
laws of motion none of them were worried
about being reductionist it because they
all believed in the great interlocking
order and they all believed in the great
chain being so they weren't worried
about anything happening to that but the
problem is they were continuing to
basically measure all of this stuff and
you can't really measure these interior
left hand subjective and inner
subjective realities very well you can
measure exterior matter well and through
the more science kept going forward the
more the Enlightenment ended up almost
accidentally with an official philosophy
of what's often called scientific
materialism and so yes we believe in the
whole interlocking order of nature but
only as far as you can see it in an
objective materialistic way it's very
holistic and spheria interwoven this is
all exterior objective truth so it has
no interiors there's no beauty there's
no morals
there's no aesthetics there's no love
there's none of that fits into a
standard Systems Theory doesn't work so
Peterson at the very least intuitively
knows that those quadrants are real
those dimensions are real and not only
that they govern how we interpret the
world around us and again that's one of
the minor true but partial aspects that
post-modernism came up with which is the
world isn't just a perception it's a
conception it's an interpretation we
have to interpret these things that we
see that's an important partial truth
and nobody denies that including
Peterson which is why the things he
attacks in post-modernism are all the
extremest regressive you know
outrageously idiotic aspects of it but
he still uses some of its core ideas
because those are real in that there and
he uses him and he knows it
but he's looking at these interpretive
schemes and he's really attempting to
find out what those are and one of his
closely allied issues to that was
looking at totalitarian systems and
saying why does that happen and became
by his own account quite obsessed with
that for decades
and I very much enjoy his conclusions
but so he has these notion of maps of
meaning and then he would frequently
start referring to those as archetype oh
and and that's the way he for example
would start interpreting religion and
and he's given all these recent you know
several hour-long talks about sort of
every aspect of Genesis and he's just
moving you know through the Bible and
doing that and all of that is it's very
important and I agree with a great deal
of that that a lot of times when it
comes to Jordan Peterson it's it's it's
not that I'll disagree with much of what
he says I agree with much of what he
says it's some of the things that he
leaves out and I find this a little bit
interesting because he's clearly an
integral thinker
and let me let me give one more example
of what second-tier means using a fairly
well researched developmental model that
was developed by Michael Commons and
Richards and they just call it a
hierarchical model but we really have to
emphasize the understanding that there
are two types of hierarchies and this is
what Greene absolutely overlooks and
it's a disaster
there are Dominator hierarchies and
there are growth hierarchies or
actualization hierarchies Dominator
hierarchies are all the horrible things
that postmodern say they are they're
tyrannical their power structures
they're oppressive they're the cause of
almost every nightmare you can think of
in human history and you want to do as
much as you can to get rid of those as
much as you possibly can but then there
are growth hierarchies those are the
opposite of done literally the opposite
of Dominator hierarchies in a dominate
are those the same thing as what
Peterson would describe as hierarchies
of competence close to it the Dominator
hierarchies the higher you go in a
Dominator hierarchy the more people you
can oppress the more people you can hurt
the more exclusive you are the higher
you go in a growth hierarchy the more
inclusive you are you actually are
including more people we saw this simple
developmental model that goes from just
me to a group to all groups to all
humans to integrating all of those
that's a growth hierarchy and the was so
ironic and horrifying is that the
postmodernist in their streamer collapse
these and so they don't see that the
values that they represent to the Sun
they represent value so egalitarian
values for example or values of identity
or diversity you're not born with those
values and out of those sort of six to
eight stages of development there's only
one stage that has those values and
that's green but green is a result of
about five stages of growth hierarchical
development and when you pull the rug
out from under all hierarchies you pull
the rug out you pull a ladder out from
getting to your own values a suicidal
it's absolutely self-destructive and so
in a sense you've almost given up on
that and that's why they end up getting
just very absolute istic and just sort
of yelling slogans and regressing to
ethnocentric and all that kind of stuff
so these higher
he's are clearly important and by the
way just that whole notion of a growth
hierarchy Peterson rather famously
traced it back to lobsters and he was
simply trying to demonstrate that the
that some of these hierarchies are
absolutely necessary we can't get around
them and they're certainly not the
product of Western capitalistic
tyrannical patriarchy they backed like
whatever's 350 million years or
something like that to to the lobsters
but in fact those kinds of growth
hierarchies which are also author
Kessler coined the term whole Larkin
because each of its stages is a whole
lung and a whole line is a whole that's
part of a larger whole and almost
everything in the in the universe is a
colon and so even if you go back into a
circuit the overall evolutionary
sequence going all the way back to the
Big Bang you're from atoms to molecules
to cells to organisms to then even more
complex differentiate involved organisms
each one of those is getting more
inclusive and they transcend and include
literally molecules go beyond atoms but
they enfold them they include them
molecules don't hate atoms they don't
oppress atoms they don't exclude atoms
if anything they love them I mean
they're actually hugging them that's
what growth hierarchies do and if you're
really serious about values of inclusion
and diversity and comprehensiveness you
need a growth hole are key you need a
growth hierarchy and by the way the only
people that use Dominator hierarchies
are people at lower stages on growth
hierarchies and everybody on a higher
stage of growth hierarchy criticizes
Dominator hierarchies that's how you get
to do it and that's why the
postmodernist were criticizing it it's
because they were at this
relatively high stage of development
even as they started to go extreme and
sort of mess it up so the one area where
I would like to see Peterson give more
attention is that is the actual amount
of research we have on growth
hierarchies in terms of some specific
stages that they go through there's a
certain reason that that those tended to
drop out of academia and that is in the
1960s as we said in 1959 the percent of
the population at green post modern
multicultural green was about 3% and
then it really started to explode during
the 60s and if you were really smart
leading-edge thinker at the time you
were green you were thinking these signs
of things you were reading Foucault and
you were reading dairy talk and you were
taking these things very seriously and
they were emphasizing contextualism they
were sizing constructivism they were
emphasizing the interplay between
perspectives that there aren't dominant
perspectives you have to take them all
into account there's all partial truths
and all of that and the smart smart
people were pushing those edges they
managed to move into education and
literally in a generation end up almost
dominating it so we have essentially a
green and often broken green a system of
education that goes all the way down to
first grade now so even in in like third
and fourth grade kids will be given
handouts on white supremacy and
you know everybody who's white has to
sort of see that and apologize for being
and all that kind of stuff so they
managed to take over education in terms
of the number of professors that were
conservative versus progressive and
about 1950 the ratio from progressive to
conservative was about four to one today
according jonathan heights research it's
about 20 to 1 as peterson will say there
just are no conservatives and human
sciences in a sense that's right and
that's a real problem in terms of
actually having a balanced overview of
these things in the 60s as Green started
to emerge and this is one of the reasons
that we don't see much of a discussion
about development in academia today as
Green came in and started to take over
evolution its major one of its major
beliefs is it all hierarchies are bad
because they've confused growth
hierarchies and Dominator priorities and
so during the 40s and 50s and some a bit
earlier we had all of these really
pioneering developmental psychologists
that were studying these areas really
for the first time and so if you look at
all of the sort of dozen or so multiple
intelligences and again if you don't
like that concept and a Peterson doesn't
like that you think about it is multiple
areas of expertise or capacity so
mathematics music cognitive development
moral development emotional development
eager development its values development
and so on all of these pine
developmentalists Canton to be focusing
on just sort of one of these lines so PA
tended to focus on cognitive development
Kohlberg tended to focus on moral
development
Maseo tended to focus on motivational
development jane Lovins you focus on ego
development they didn't have a real good
understanding of that at that time but
the research they were doing was really
good and the stages they came up with
again showed both the differences that
were actually there because they were
each them looking at a different
developmental line of development but
the stages were essentially similar and
you could map those across all of these
lines but in the 60s as Green starts to
emerge and come into the culture and
particularly as it starts to take over
academia what started to happen is that
all systems that had anything to do with
hierarchies were thrown out and
developmental psychology itself was just
devastated by that I mean there were
entire departments of developmental
psychology just closing down and so a
lot of the really really great
developmental is the really pioneering
ones that we still look at today in a
sense they all circled the wagons is the
Harvard Graduate School of Education and
so you know interestingly they weren't
in the psychology department
the psychology had already gotten rid of
all those nasty hierarchies but in
education you actually had to produce
results you had to actually educate
people so you actually had to know the
stages they went through so all of these
developmentalist SAR over in the Harvard
Graduate School of Education I mean
really the great ones um Lawrence
Kohlberg was there Jane Levinger was
there Fisher was there Howard Gardner
was there Robert Keegan was there I mean
it was outrageous and and they're still
over there basically
doing that and at interval Institute we
sent a lot of students out to distending
with them these are some really really
great people people like Robert Keegan
and so but the whole even topic of
developmental studies was just
immediately read as a wingman you're
saying this person is better than this
person and in Renault and that's not
what they're saying
I mean you mr. social activist you're
saying it's better not to be prejudiced
you're saying it's better to be to treat
all people fairly regardless of race
color sex or creed that's exactly what
growth hierarchies are saying they said
that those values are the result of
several stages of growth you're not at
six months old you're not born with
those values and you're running around
the little you know sign protesting but
it just sort of fell out of academia
discussion almost entirely and even
smart people who know about the
importance of hierarchies and the
difference between competence
hierarchies and inequality hierarchies
it's just not a topic that tends to
enter their awareness because mostly in
any of the schooling they got it really
wasn't a topic ever and services
something is kind of dropped off the
radar and it's one of the reasons that
when we talk about an integral framework
those are one of the areas that we
include because there is an enormous
amount of evidence for them and in
particular they have such a strong
explanatory power they help us
understand what's happening and what and
and the sort of summary of all of that
is that as we look at the culture wars
what we find just in terms of
developmental studies is that it's in
this this whole first tier set of stages
the highest three the three that are
most recently occurred and are still
present everybody is born in square one
and has to move through these so we
still have a fair number of people at
ethnocentric fair enough people at
orange world centric and fair another
number people at green multicultural but
those upper three are at each other's
throats they really don't like each
other
they've increasingly come to hate each
other in many ways and they're at each
other's throats and the problem is
because their offers tear they can't
solve that problem ever was by
definition first here thinks that if
dyes are the only correct ones but
second tier that has the inherent
capacity to see the importance of all of
these and at least start thinking about
ways okay since everybody has to go
through all of these then an enlightened
society would include ways to help us do
that and so that's one of the things
that is a way out of the culture wars in
addition to whatever else we might need
to do and there are plenty of other
things but this is crucial because if we
still have people that really are at
values that are absolutely committed to
not integrating everything then you're
not going to get them integrated ever
there's no motivation that wants to do
that and so that's why a second tier
integral orientation becomes so
important and that's why people that are
really looking to help draw together
paradigms and cross paradigms to
actually integrate then these number of
different disciplines and approaches
become so absolutely crucial there's a
big debate in many integral communities
about jordan peterson and one of the
most frequently expressed perspectives
is
how can he be integral when he is so
anti green if you look at just the
actual developmental maps of what
happens at these stages if you look at
Commons and Richards for example or if
you look at Kurt Fisher if you look at
any of the stages that are trying to say
specifically ok this is what happens in
mathematical reasoning or in cognitive
reasoning or in emotional awareness or
in aesthetics or so on
and they lay them out as I said one or
several of the things that tend to get
laid out at the meta systemic level one
is that it's just that it's meta
systemic it introduces the fourth person
perspective it just means it can reflect
on the universal third-person
perspectives that orange brought into
existence and that we're so profound for
the Western world but that fourth person
perspective is a capacity to actually
reflect on that and make sort of certain
critical announcements about it it can
appreciate it or it can disagree with it
but it can do that
Peterson does that he's fully aware of
doing that he's using that meta systemic
capacity but he also has the capacity
for paired ematic and and and cross pair
demanded thinking so he doesn't just
reflect on those things he tries to tie
them together I mean he he'll say one of
the things for example that Piaget was
trying to do was to integrate science
and religion and that's one of the
things that he very much wants to do and
so he does he is making use of those
capacities although he's also
transcended and included so he's using
capacities that will encompass the
limitations of having just that stage
this is just that stage
gets lost in radical Galit arianism and
relativism and all of that it's not a
really good stage to only have access to
but he doesn't he has access to paradigm
attic and cross very dramatic stuff in
terms of anger this the fact that you're
at an integral stage doesn't mean that
first of all it doesn't mean that you
have you can have no shadow elements you
do you're just repressing elements from
the integral stages and that certainly
can happen and so and he no shadow
material very well and he's made a
enormous amount of giving an enormous
amount of studying to it particularly in
the line of young I said he knows his
own shadow and and and I'm sure he's
perfectly aware that he still has some
of it I think that his anger is one that
is in a sense a type of it's almost a
kind of existential anger it's almost a
kind of anger that looks at something
that just from the most number of
perspectives seems just patently wrong
is patently mistaken now again I you
know I think every discipline has some
degree of truth because I don't think
any disciplines capable just being 100%
wrong there'd be no reason it would be
adopted if it was just nothing but wrong
every time he tried it you would give it
up but they can do things that are so
dysfunctional and they can be so broken
and that's one of the things that's
happened to leading-edge Green it is a
fundamentally broken green and that's
for example in
I did this book on Trump in a post truth
world and tried to indicate how that
broken green was a large part of that
political movement that we're seeing
today and that's the problem with green
it's not a healthy leading-edge and
that's a real real problem because it is
leading-edge what's starting to take
over that leading edge is second tier
because again we have about 5% 6% there
when it gets closer to 10% then it's
officially going to be a leading edge
and there's going to be some sort of
tipping point we're going to see that
happening so in terms of any number of
individuals in the dark web who again
most of them I think are operating with
integral cognitive capacities doesn't
stop any of them from having very
specific existential anger issues and
things that they see and think that are
wrong I think that if you sit down and
actually look at the items that are
included in each particular stage and
see how those fundamental items are
taken up and included in the next stage
and then those are taken up and included
in the next stage I think people could
see how somebody like Jordan Peterson is
making use of those fundamental
intrinsic factors of that stage but a
lot of people say he doesn't try and
send don't include green you think he
does I I think he does and I think the
part of green that he doesn't like is
the extremists identity politics
neo-marxist aspects and my point is
simply that if you look at virtually any
developmental model of cognitive
development you will see a stage of
development that's variously recalled
dialectical
or relativistic or multicultural or
whatever it is and it's just introducing
a new perspective that can then reflect
on the previous perspective and that
perspective can reflect on the previous
perspective and so on
and those are real capacities real
characteristics and those are included
in almost every dark web intellectual
that we have but then you're allowed to
get angry with various aspects of any of
these things and that anger might be
what you could call just sort of a pure
entirely justified anger or it could be
some of your own shadow material
nobody ever ultimately escapes all
shadow material it's always there and I
would develop a show if I have some
shadow material it runs in the direction
that you're in Petersons does which is
I've sort of been riding in this general
field now for maybe 50 years and so I
just watched daily the postmodern
theorists come in and initially they
were making interesting points but then
they got caught in relativism that
started to generate into Neil ISM and
narcissism and I just went off the deep
end
and we completely lost almost any of the
value at that point and that was very
disturbing and very angry making for me
it really was in Fury you share his
anger it's right you share his anger oh
yeah very much and I see some of the
positive factors that led it to become
the postmodern movement I mean the whole
point about there's traditionalism than
there was modernism then there was
post-modernism those are very real
developmental unfoldings because that's
the point that many people would say you
and he differ is that he doesn't seem to
see any positive value in post-modernism
that's right and
I believe it's because there's been this
enormous downplay in academia of looking
at almost any of the real developmental
sequences so again if you look at Piaget
and-and-and or even even call young
I mean Peterson says that the single
best book on Jungian psychology is it's
Eric von neumann's I think origin
history consciousness and I happen to
agree I was absolutely blown away by
that book I read it several times and
even outlined it two or three times but
the whole point about his book was these
stages that consciousness went through
any stage had a different cognitive
capacity he stays saw the world
completely differently there are
different world views at all of these
and that's was so profoundly stunning
about the developmental of your point
and it certainly too appears a but that
never to Smashing
with Jordan I've never heard him say oh
and there's a worldview down here that
looks like this and in the world here
looks like this
Peter said his stages even though he
loves Pichet that aspect of
developmental studies just got shoved
off the burner
and so if he were actually looking for
example at the ingredients that each of
these stages add I don't think he would
disagree with any of those ingredients
and given the fact that we have a fair
amount of evidence that these things
have to emerge in stages because the
whole of one stage actually becomes an
ingredient of the whole of the next
stage so they are whole ons the whole of
one stage is part of the next stage the
whole of that stage is part of that
stage so you can't actually get to a
higher stage without including that
lower stage and so what are we including
well pre-operational you're including
the passage for images and then concept
symbols and in concepts and then rules
and form operational matter rules and
then systemic paradigms and in Kraus
paradigms and these are first person
second person third person fourth person
fifth person perspectives all of those
are added I don't think he disagrees of
any of those and particularly if you
actually looked at okay here's the skill
that you add here here's the skill you
had here and so on
and it received these broad broad stages
or that kind of development I don't
think he'd have any trouble with that
and if he did then I would just say well
I agree with these hundred developmental
maps that do you see evidence in those
and I understand that you don't and
that's fine but much more common
nowadays are things like the big five
factor analysis I totally agree with
that it's part of what we call types
actual ingredient or the internal
framework we totally include that but
again types you something that say
essentially the same no matter what
stage you're at you can start to shift a
little bit but basically they stay the
same that's what a type is and so and it
also goes for example and if you even
talk about types of male and female
interaction or interest the traits those
stay essentially similar as you grow and
develop so you can look at all the
things that all these stages have in
common and that's fine they're real
they're there but so are the stages I
mean that's sort of the whole point
because you have these dramatically
different world views about how things
look and act and what they mean and
they're they're they're real and they're
an enormous explanatory power so that's
one of the areas that that we include in
these 567 aspects of an integral in a
remodel and you you just mentioned male
and female and that's that's something
that Peterson has been criticized for
quite a lot he for equating the
masculine with order and the feminine
with chaos this is a theological point
and maybe it's a simplified theological
point
what what do you make of that
perspective it's not my favorite aspect
of what he does I can agree with the
importance of order and chaos and even
to some extent the way he connects it
with left and right brain hemisphere and
that these are two of the very very
fundamental dualisms that this
manifested world is made of but but the
direct connection of and he doesn't just
identify he doesn't say the female is
chaos and
male disorder he says female is symbolic
of it doesn't make it much better though
that doesn't I don't find that a
terribly compelling piece of information
and and I find that it does that there
are other ways to if you're going to try
to describe just general statistical
differences between men and women that
one of them is symbolic of chaos and one
of them is symbolic of order it's not
one of the ones that we find very useful
and I don't think a whole lot of either
men or women directly connect with that
I don't think they find that very
meaningful he also of course will
identify in general and that's that's
one of the problems not many people
understand statistics and so if you say
60 percent of the most aggressive people
are men and 40 percent are women people
will think you're saying you know that
it's just either/or and that's just one
of the problems is that people that
aren't really sophisticated on these
things are really misinterpreting what
he's saying anyway I wanted to bring in
something I've heard David data say
before
theologically you can identify the
masculine principle with the witnessing
consciousness and the feminine with the
witnessed it does that help is that a
mall is that a definition that might
help expand this perspective well at
this point what you are getting into is
a lot of different types of systems that
you know the fact that men and women
have been on this planet for you know a
couple million years there have been at
least certain types of differences that
we've noticed nothing else women give
birth and lactate men on average have a
slightly greater upper body strength so
you can take a really brilliant feminist
systems theorists like Janet chef is and
she'll say that what we have to do in
order to understand the differences in
the different roles that men and women
have had is that we do have to start
with at least a few biological
universals and then look at how those
play themselves out in different
techno-economic modes for example and
that's an important type of addition
it's part of what we call showing up in
integral because we're looking at all
four quadrants and the techno-economic
mode is the lower right quadrant if
you're looking at a society from an
exterior objective fashion and the men
the stages that are often used there for
example are Gerhard Lenski who came up
with the stages of foraging or hunting
and gathering and then horticultural
agrarian industrial and informational
and janice athis took just those two
biological differences ensured how they
produce dramatically different roles for
men and women at these different
techno-economic modes
one of the reasons you have to take
quadrants into account when you make
these kinds of statements so even given
those differences that are pretty hard
to deny at least in terms of biological
where we say upper right exterior of an
individual viewpoint and foraging
sexuals were just barely being
differentiated anyway but the men tended
to do those items that required upper
body strength so they tended to do
hunting and would tend to be more
warriors and then women tended to give
birth and lactate and they just sort of
played played that out when you get to
horticultural you start to see a real
shift where the cultural is the first
form of farming and it's defined as
farming that just uses a simple digging
stick or hoe and the important thing
about that is a pregnant woman can do
that kind of farming without any real
harm to her and chef has estimates that
in horticultural societies about 80% of
the fruit stuff were produced by women
and so they clearly are having an
enormous impact in the public productive
sphere they're not just in the private
reproductive sphere and as a matter of
fact in horticultural societies one
study showed that approximately one
third of horticultural societies had
female only deities and these are all
the great mothers societies and when
these matriarchy societies were first
discovered under the patio erekle
society here's a massive discovery is
like wow and of course the feminists
jumped all over is like you know women
were first and then men took it away and
all adapt it was a huge discovery and it
was discovering just this horticultural
base and the way that took differences
in human biology but still played them
out very differently in terms of roles
men were still kind of trying to go off
into hunting and stuff
but women were producing 80% of the food
because that was coming from farming and
so they had a role in the public
productive sphere and again about a
third of those of those deities are
female only and that's almost the only
place you find that whenever you find a
great mother society it tends to be
quite a cultural well then agrarian came
into being that was farming done with an
extremely heavy animal-drawn plow now
greatest chef is women that did that
suffered an extremely high rate of
miscarriage and it was to their
Darwinian advantage not to do that plus
the just the heaviness of the damn thing
tended to select for men in their upper
body strength and so there was a big
change and one of the things that we
find there were other causes but looking
at this omelet this is an almost Marxist
orientation but the deities and agrarian
cultures are oat 95% are male only and
if you want to start talking about
something like a patriarchy that's where
you could really start to point at that
and say that's really patriarchal
Chavez's point is that but you can't
just say it's oppression women were
choosing not to do that and there are
actually some studies of those kinds of
patriarchal cultures history quality of
life was much less for men than it was
for women nevertheless women did tend to
then be in the private reproductive
sphere men in the public productive
sphere and that tended to start to get
that kind of patriarchal orientation
again you had to be very careful about
saying that was just men oppressing
women that's something that really
drives Peterson crazy and I share some
of that because
takes away the agency of women and and I
found that one of the most disturbing
factors of the feminists theories that
tried to do that and try to blame all
female conditions to oppression because
it takes away their agency as if they
actually had nothing to say or do about
these societies but as they really were
contributing in at least some important
ways to how these were done I don't know
what women
there's feminists know that think that
women were just acquiesce like sheep to
everything that the man did to control
them but these aren't the women I know I
died there I don't know where they're
finding these women but apparently that
happened then when you start to get to
industrial cultures now you start to get
a real shift because now machines are
doing the work on nature that human
bodies used to have to do and that takes
that pressure out so now there's no
longer as strong a selection for male
body upper strength and female birth and
lactation and so here we start to see
again universal modes of morality we
start to see the rise of the women's
movement we start to see the freeing of
slaves and abolition and all of this is
going against the traditional roles that
were laid down during agrarian which is
men do all the public making decisions
women's stay home and run the household
in the family and those were rules that
both of them were stuck with it's not
like one of those was a whole lot of fun
and the other was miserable I mean men
died a year sooner they had to fight in
war that virtually all of the death
inducing jobs they had the state could
force them to give their lives weren't
feral call them the disposable sexes
I mean just it wasn't that the they just
had it all bad
but they didn't have it all good it
wasn't like they arranged the society
that gave them the best of everything
and women the worst of everything
because if they did that they did a
shitty job so I just think that can't be
an idealistic version for men it can't
be
so then as we move into informational
then there's even less drive for
physical force and what we're facing now
is this possibility that men and women
just have different interests and now
they're more free to express them and so
Peterson's point about that is that in
countries like Scandinavia where you
have the most freedom for men and women
they actually show the greatest
differences in terms of preferences and
so what's that all about
well it's not just oppression it could
be some but the oppression also remember
is basically modernity gets blamed for
all of these horrifying
rules but modernity was halfway through
the Cure they were starting to get rid
of these agrarian roles which were very
patriarchal again not necessarily just
the oppression but just through the
differentiation of what the sessions did
and the absolute brutality of nature and
what we had to do just to stay alive and
that didn't include men having councils
all the time trying to figure out how to
oppress women
it was mostly men and women thinking
together what are we going to do to
manage to stay alive and yes there was
oppression and that was during an
ethnocentric era so of course there was
racism and slavery and one tribe against
other tribes and all of that those roles
are what the modern rational industrial
societies started to overcome and then
they become even more so in information
and what we're trying to do now is
because we have this leading-edge green
which is bro
again mostly not allowing us to even
discuss these issues because everything
simply has to be equal outcome and if
it's not there's discrimination there's
sexism there's racism there's something
going on and again the difficulties that
it's not that those aren't occurring
it's just those are only occurring there
are other reasons that it's occurring
and those aren't necessarily bad those
have to be allowed or else are going to
start erasing those as well and you're
going to end up doing what you did with
hierarchies you're going to try to get
rid of all the Dominator hierarchies and
you're gonna get rid of all the growth
hierarchies and then you can have to get
no way to even grow to the values that
you're trying to get established you've
lost the path to it so all you can do is
protest and yell and scream and doesn't
do any good at all
so there's a theological point like a
lot of people are critical of Jordan
Peterson because on some level he's
doing a really important role of
restoring the role of the father in some
sense but there is a sense that he's
looking back to like he's trying to
restore Christian values and very
masculine religious values could it be
that actually we're seeing a theological
shift so the kind of theology that we're
moving into is more of a balance between
masculine and feminine because as you've
said that the role of of men and women
is changing so actually what we don't we
don't necessarily need a restoration of
the sort of God the Father maybe what we
need is a different theological
synthesis well I think that's part of
the difficulties that come and they they
come in part because we leave out that
developmental component so we were
talking a bit earlier about just the
sort of Janet chef has few which which I
find there there's some genuine truth to
that as part of a overall integral
framework
but you can see how there were shifts
from more mature focal societies to more
Patra focal societies and then two
societies start to try to overcome those
and those new stages of development
certainly industrialization and
information to the extent that those had
in effect on our culture and they did
they're not something you found in the
Bible there's not something you found in
early civilization now Jordan my sake
yeah but we had the seeds for all that
there and go right but notice that still
took a while to unfold and many of those
early stages didn't have that and many
of these existential or even
transcendental important Givens that
were being embedded in religion those
also tended to unfold even though we can
find in the judeo-christian tradition
this tendency that would eventually lead
to individual rights even if it wasn't
that often expressed in a full extent in
the original orientation and
particularly since most of the world's
great religions did arise during
appearance like the great axial period
roughly a millennia or so BCE
those really were the error GE Epps's
error of just the modern mythic era and
and for a lot of the religions created
at that time there were again these two
different aspects there was a very small
number they were involved in waking up
actually having this transformative
Satori experience of altering the unity
consciousness but most of them were just
okay what do I have to do to stay on the
good side of this god what do I have to
do here or here's
history of my people or something like
that when it says Moses parted the Red
Sea when that was first written when the
person sat down and wrote Moses parted
the Red Sea they didn't have some deep
symbolic meaning to that it didn't mean
oh the Israelites had to overcome a lot
of problems and we look to our leader
Moses and he could he could help do away
with with blockades like moving a Red
Sea and that was all symbolic and then
we moved out and found our own promise
that's not what the person meant when
they wrote Moses parted the Red Sea they
meant this guy named Moses stood next to
the Red Sea and he went back and the sea
parted and they walked across that's
what he meant and so again when James
Fowler was actually measuring these
developmental stages of religious belief
systems and again like most about mental
models he found six to eight major
stages of development and they were
versions of archaic to magic to mythic
rational pluralistic and integral most
of these weren't he actually called
mythic literal because the myths were
meant literally
and so you'll notice when Peterson tells
us the meaning of Genesis or the meaning
of exes or those kinds of things he
doesn't agree with the literal meaning
and the literal meaning is what the
original writers meant that's what they
were saying but he's trying to read
something deeper into that and that
might be there and in to some extent of
course it is simply because societies
have not only their explicit conscious
understandings for those sorts of
infrastructure interactions and
mechanical systems that are occurring
that we know nothing about or don't
really understand so all that's fine and
we do have this whole left hand first
and second person implicit rules
and patterns of behavior that we're
really not that much aware of so he it's
okay for him looking for those but one
of the reasons I hate he won't himself
just say yeah I believe that he doesn't
believe Moses really parted the Red Sea
not literally so that's not what he's
talking about and and this is a little
bit where the problem comes in because
if you're going to do that and you're
going to look for these underlying rules
and patterns really best evidence is
that those unfold those develop those
have changed we don't look at human
sacrifice the way we did 4,000 years ago
there are different implicit rules for
that we did do that it archaic to magic
periods but then we crew out of those
and there are different grammars
different rules at each of these stages
and the same goes for how men and women
have interacted even if we agree with
let's say a big five statistical
analysis that men have more
industriousness and women have more
agreeableness and negative emotions say
okay that's fine
but just as we saw with you Janet chef
is analysis of the male and female roles
at different tech North anomic eras even
though it's the same biology there can
be these differences in terms of what's
masculine and what's feminine and so if
we want to choose some of those things
that have some sort of truth today and
then we're going to track them all the
way back you know to three thousand
years ago we have to be very careful
about how we do that and one of the
things that I think will help Peterson's
explanation of religion
if he does look at these different
stages of religion the actual beliefs as
they unfolded and not simply sort of put
them all together as a single narrative
and then try to read the existential
underlying rules for all of them that's
that that's a little bit dicey if you
really are looking at different ways
that human beings develop through their
spiritual understandings and again I'll
just mention James Fowler very quickly
he was one of the pioneers that was
looking at these different capacities
that humans have in this case he looked
at something that we recall spiritual
intelligence so like cognitive
intelligence emotional intelligence
moral intelligence there's a spiritual
intelligence that's different from
direct spiritual experience direct
spiritual experience that's waking up
again we can talk a little bit about
that because Petersen is perfectly aware
of waking up and he absolutely aware of
it but he doesn't really talk about that
so he talks about more than growing up
components and how that happened but he
doesn't take a look at some of these
different stages like capsules archaic
magic mythic into rational with the
Western culture and then into the
multicultural pluralistic post-modernism
valor found that and he defined God the
way Tillich did as concern as an
ultimate concern so whatever your
ultimate concern is if you make a list
of the most important of the most
important of the most important things
in your life whatever the top of that
list is is your ultimate important thing
that's your God what ever it is it could
be atheism and you're still using
spiritual intelligence because whenever
you think about ultimate realities
that's what you're engaged and that's
the intelligence that you activate when
you think like that and the faller found
that it really did go through these
distinct identifiable stages and then we
can combine that with people attend
historical work like jean gebser you see
some real similarities and in those
things and they are profoundly different
I mean you really can have a spiritual
worldview that's magic voodoo tends to
be an example of magic magic is the idea
and it tends to occur and developmental
sequences fairly early because the human
organism is learning to differentiate
itself from the environment and in the
process was learning to do that it
hasn't quite succeeded and so it's
mental image of a thing isn't really
real differentiated from the thing so it
thinks that to manipulate its mental
idea of the thing is to actually
magically change the thing so if I make
a doll that represents you and I stick a
pin in the doll I've actually hurt you
that's magic and we all have magic we
love superstition but that tends to be
when the earliest stages of cognitive
development where the earliest stages of
spiritual intelligence and so on and it
is magic as it starts to move towards
mythic you get a stage that Spile
dynamics for example calls power gods
because you realize there's still magic
or you think there's still magic in the
world but it's you don't have it anymore
you keep trying it really doesn't work
so you sort of give up but others have
it so mommy for example could change the
yucky spinach into candy if she wanted
because she's a power God and so if you
want to be on the good side of your
power God you have to know how to be
nice to it you have to know what it
wants to say and develop these whole
rituals or types of prayers and so on
and eventually that magic retreat
Senta just supernatural beings series
sir Apollo Yahweh God that kind of thing
and then you get the magic stage and
that occurs on up until you get the
emergence of rational which has the
third-person perspective reflects on
that goes those are really real if I
want something I'm gonna have to do it
myself through scientific experiment and
and research so so you're seeing those
kinds of development occur in religion
and and what Peterson does is he won't
himself profess belief in any of what
those stages actually say and he said he
doesn't really believe that Moses
actually parted the Red Sea he doesn't
really believe that Lot's wife was
turned into a pillar of salt but that's
what the people that had that belief
that's what they believed
now how much they are also being
influenced by these hidden factors that
he sees what was really happening that's
a little bit more open to debate I think
they are there but I think you do you
see shifts as development undergoes
because they just aren't the same
fundamental rules at those different
kinds of viewpoints and you had to take
those into account and so that's one of
the concerns with that now his argument
Sam Harris is Harris focus is exactly on
what they're saying and that's what he
says and that's wrong and so he'll
actually criticize Moses really parting
the Red Sea and he'll say that's just
false we don't need it get rid of it and
then Peterson is again and Sam is doing
it because he he's not an eliminative
materialism but he does still tend to
kind of reduce everything to third
person determined causality and there's
no room for freedom in
and in that at all and so he'll he'll
take all of those actual literal
statements of religion leading up to
science and you'll say all of that is
just flat-out bloody wrong it has no
business being there it was a stupid
mistake we made from the beginning it's
still around we've got to get rid of it
nothing good and he's altering from that
third-person deterministic scientific
stance and Peterson is always going to
know wait a minute
there are these interior left-hand
subjective and inner subjective
realities and yeah okay it's not
actually Moses parting the Red Sea but
it is these really existential means
that help us develop value systems in
the first place including a value for
third person science that you just don't
get that out of midair that comes from
this implicit belief system that you can
see in these religions but this is where
they really are at cross-purposes
because they're not really arguing the
same thing at all and both of them are
leaving out these developmental stages
so what Sam really doesn't like is magic
and mythic viewers of ultimate concern
he doesn't like them in Islam he doesn't
like them in Christianity he doesn't
like them wherever he sees them and at
the time that they existed it was in a
sense the best we could do but today yes
you can do better in terms of the types
of truth that might be attempting
attempting to be disclosed there you can
do better in many cases using a type of
scientific third-person approach but
there still are all these interiors and
they still have various rules and
patterns to govern them and you can't
get those just through an objective view
of science and that's where Sam is
always holding out the last thing I want
to say just very quickly is that both of
them are fully aware of waking
up and neither of them include that in
their argument and it's weird because
the actual super core of a spiritual
system is the system of waking up it's
not developing a series of beliefs that
okay I believe Moses really did that and
yes I believe Christ really was born
from a biological version and if I agree
to everything it says in the apostle
creed which is a list of myths and I
believe everything says in the Nicene
Creed another list of myths and I signed
on the bottom line that's it I'm a
Christian I'm saved forever in a mythic
world view and then so on that's not
what ultimate spirituality is about even
the Christian mystics would do more like
what st. Paul said let this
consciousness be in you which was in
Christ Jesus that we all may be one
that's a fairly good description of
ultimate unity consciousness
that's what around the world there are
various daily sub branches of religion
that know about this and it's called
enlightenment awakening Sanskrit is
moksha pure freedom its Satori it's the
great liberation
[Music]
you